<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To all people that speakes of an outvvard baptisme; dippers, sprinklers, and others Also the errors answered, holden forth by Thomas Larkham, called by the world a minister, at VVe[x]ford he was then with a reproofe to the offenders; and also some queries to all people to be read within that yee may all know that, that which may bee knowne of God is manifest within; Rom: 1: 19...  From a friend to all that breath after jesus; known to the world by the name Humphry Norton; though amongst the scorners called a Qvaker.</title>
            <author>Norton, Humphrey, fl. 1655-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1312A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222710</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833853</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833853</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38331</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38331)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2213:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To all people that speakes of an outvvard baptisme; dippers, sprinklers, and others Also the errors answered, holden forth by Thomas Larkham, called by the world a minister, at VVe[x]ford he was then with a reproofe to the offenders; and also some queries to all people to be read within that yee may all know that, that which may bee knowne of God is manifest within; Rom: 1: 19...  From a friend to all that breath after jesus; known to the world by the name Humphry Norton; though amongst the scorners called a Qvaker.</title>
                  <author>Norton, Humphrey, fl. 1655-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Gathered in 2's.</note>
                  <note>P. 9 misnumbered p. 8.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Larkham, Thomas, 1602-1669 --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38331:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO ALL PEOPLE THAT SPEAKES OF AN OVTVVARD BAPTISME; <hi>DIPPERS, SPRINKLERS, AND OTHERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo the Errors anſwered, holden forth by THOMAS LARKHAM Called by the World a Miniſter, at <hi>VVexford</hi> he was then With a reproofe to the Offenders; And alſo ſome Que<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ries to all people to be read within that yee may all know that, That which may bee knowne of God is manifeſt within; <hi>Rom:</hi> 1: 19.</p>
            <p>
               <q>WE are the Circumciſion which worſhip God in the Spirit, &amp; rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh <bibl>
                     <hi>Phillipians:</hi> 3: 3.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <q>For he is not a Jew which is one outwardly neither is that Circumciſion which is outward in the fleſh, but he is a Jew which is one inwardly; and Circumciſion is that of the heart in the Spirit, and not in the Letter; whoſe praiſe is not of men but of God; <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom:</hi> 2: 28: 29.</bibl>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>FRom a friend to all that breath after JESUS; known to the world by the Name, <hi>Humphry Norton;</hi> Though amongſt the Scorners called a <hi>QVAKER.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are the Circumciſion which worſhip God in the Spirit; and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have noe confidence in the fleſh, <hi>Phillipians.</hi> 3: 3.</p>
            <p>For he is not a Jew, which is one outwardly, neither is that Circumciſion which is outward in the fleſh but he is a Jew which is one inwardly &amp; Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion is that of the heart in the Spirit, &amp; not in the letter, whoſe praiſe is not of men but of God; <hi>Rom.</hi> 2: 28: 29.</p>
            <p>To all you every where that goes under the Name of <hi>Baptiſts, Dippers, Sprinklers,</hi> and others, to the Light in all your conſciences I ſpeake, let it anſwer, which ſhews you that you are waſhing your ſelves, remember the Scribes and Phariſees, who were compared to the Cup and Platter, waſhing the out-ſide, but inwardly were Ravening Woolues; you waſh your ſelves, &amp; one waſhing another, And you all diſhonour Chriſt, and will neither come to him your ſelves, nor ſuffer others; and except he waſh you, yee have noe part
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38331:2"/>
in him, Therfore I ſay leave that ſelfe waſhing, &amp; take up the Croſs to your ſelves, that ſelfe may be crucified, &amp; all ſelfe, &amp; ſelfe Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs waſhed away; That the waſhing, and renewing, and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating, of the holy Ghoſt, yee may know and witneſs, as <hi>Paul</hi> did; who laboured to bring people to the ſame, and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn:</hi> they were Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, ſo that the chief Prieſts, and Scribes, and Phariſees tooke knowledge of them; that they had been with Chriſt after that he was Sacrifiſed up: And <hi>Aquilla</hi> and <hi>Priſcil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> who taught <hi>Appollos</hi> a more perfect way, then <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme; <hi>Acts:</hi> 4: 8: 13. and <hi>Acts:</hi> 18: 25: 26. for that muſt decreaſe, as ſaith <hi>Iohn:</hi> I muſt decreaſe, he muſt increaſe, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3: 30. all that ſtands in water Baptiſme; you are not come to the increaſe, which hath noe end, nor to the more perfect way (to wit) Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith I am the way, <hi>Iohn:</hi> 14: 6. which <hi>Aquilla</hi> &amp; <hi>Priſcilla</hi> taught <hi>Appollas;</hi> although he were an Elequent man: And <hi>Paul</hi> knew a more perfect Baptiſme, then that with water; when he thanked God that he Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized none of them, ſave <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius</hi> &amp;c. For he was not ſent to Baptize but to Preach 1, <hi>Cor.</hi> 1: 14: 15: 16: 17. And <hi>Paul</hi> did the worke given him to finiſh, and brought many up to perfection; and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them a more perfect way then carnall things (to wit) Chriſt Ieſus, the ſure foundation into which the <hi>Iſralits</hi> were Baptized, &amp; eate &amp; dranke of the ſame Rocke; 1: <hi>Cor: 2: 6. 1: Cor</hi> 10: 23: 4: 5.</p>
            <p>Come now yee that pleads, and Preaches up water Baptiſme, let us reaſon together; where is the cloud yee were Baptized into, is it yet removed; where is the Sea you paſſed through, which ſhall be noe more? know yee ſuch a thing? where is the Death witneſſed, and Repentance, and Remiſſion of Sin, amongſt you? To that of God in all your Conſciences I appeale, have not you water Baptized peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple yet to repent? when you are Quiet in ſpirit, is not your Sins brought freſh againſt you committed, before you were Baptized? &amp; are you not yet living in Sin? you are not yet Dead with Chriſt, nor your old man is not yet crucified; nor the body of Sin is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; <hi>Rom:</hi> 6: 6: 7: that henceforth you ſhould not ſerve it, (but come to our Baptiſme and henceforth you ſhall not ſerve Sin.) for being Dead with Chriſt, we are freed from Sin, as ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he that is dead, is freed from Sin, but yee your ſelves are alive, making a fair ſhew in the fleſh, and would conſtraine others to be Baptized, that you might Glory in their fleſh, leaſt you and they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38331:2"/>
ſhould ſuffer perſecution, for the Croſs of Chriſt &amp;c. <hi>Gall:</hi> 6: from 12: to the end; I ſay this is fleſhly Glory, the Jew outward; and the Circumciſion that availeth not, being Strangers to the life of God, to the Jew inward, and the Circumciſion of the heart with the Spirit of the living God, which is only witneſſed through the Croſs of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the pure water, whereby the Conſcience is ſprinkl'd from dead workes, &amp; the anſwer returned thou art good; but while you live in Pride, and Covetouſneſs, Luſts, and uncleanneſs, a pure Conſcience you know not, nor nothing that pure is; the light in your conſciences is my witneſs, wch will manifeſt unto you that outward water, nor noe outward thing can take away one ſin. Therefore take warning yee ſelfe waſhers, you diſhonor God, whilſt in theſe things you ſtand, which cannot perfect as pertaining to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>Heb:</hi> 9: 9: 10: But ſtand not there, for you cannot ſatisfie, that of God in your conſciences, with an Imitation from the Letter; and with telling how <hi>Phillip</hi> Baptized the <hi>Eunuch;</hi> it were well for you, if you could ſee your ſelves, in the <hi>Eunuchs</hi> condition, that you have the Scriptures and underſtand not what you read; (<hi>Acts</hi> 8: from 30: to the end) but from ſimplicity of heart would confeſs as he did, for in plainnes you underſtand not the Scriptures nor the powr of God; who tells of being Baptized, and are yet alive in your ſins; And hath to repent after you are Baptized; for which in Scripture you have neither preſept nor example; but <hi>Phillip</hi> ſhewed the <hi>Eunuch</hi> from that Scripture; an example (Chriſt) how he was lead like a Lamb, and his life was taken up from the Earth &amp;c: See if it be ſo with you, that you are taken up with him from the Earth, and all earthly things, for untill you come to know Chriſt to Guide you and Lead you to be Baptized; you have not learned the Doctrin of Baptiſme, <hi>Heb:</hi> 6: 2. for all men come unto him <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. 6. Then will you ſee that which lead the <hi>Eunuch</hi> to be Baptized, And that alſo which caught <hi>Phillip</hi> away from Baptizing, &amp; was carryed forth to preach through the Cities; The ſame ſpirit caught <hi>Paul</hi> from Baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; And made him thanke God, that he Baptized none of them, ſave <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> &amp;c. For he was not ſent to Baptize but to Preach, and he alſo Preached through the Cities, and converted many to the one Lord, and to the one Faith; and the one Baptiſme, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 5. 6. And told them if you be Dead with Chriſt from the Rudiments &amp;c. Why as though living in the world, are you ſubject unto Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38331:3"/>
touch not; taſt not; handle not; they all periſh with the uſeing, <hi>Coll.</hi> 2. 14. 20. 21. 22. And are only uſed amongſt theſe who are in the periſhing Nature, who are Enemies to the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and comes not to ſee your ſelves and your ſins; &amp; your Rudiments, Nayled to the Croſs; And therein is power to lay down your lives and take them up again, and to ſee the Scriptures fulfiled in you, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, who was crucified to the world, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 9. 10. And the world to him; his life was taken up from the earth; and noe more he, but Chriſt lived in him; and was become an high Prieſt of a more perfect tabernacle, and a mediator of a better Covenant; then that which ſtands in Meats, and Drinks, and divers Waſhings, and carnall Ordinances impoſed upon them, untill the time of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. Now theſe that ſtands in the divers waſhings, they are not come to the light, which brings to Reformation, and from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the divers waſhers, wch are in the world where they lie in ſin &amp; wickedneſs, one ſprinkling an Infant, others diping young people, (others goes in; and ſome are thrown in, and here are the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers waſhers; which waſheth the out-ſide, which ſtands in Meats, and Drinks, and carnall Ordinances, which cannot make the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers thereunto perfect, as pertaining to the conſcience; Therfore I ſay unto you all; to the light turn your mindes; which leads up to the Life, to the meaſure and ſtature and fulneſs of Chriſt; to a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 12. 13. by him to know your hearts &amp; conſciences waſhed, and purged, and ſprinkled from all evill; by his eternall ſpirit, and to ſee the Law of Commandements contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Ordinances aboliſhed in his fleſh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 15. and you draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nigh unto him through the vaile (that is to ſay) his fleſh; he that readeth, let him underſtand, and an end put to all tipes, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, and ſhaddowes; beleeving in the Light, obeying and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Light the Day breaks forth, and the ſhaddows flees away. And ſo comes to have fellowſhip with the Saints in the Light, and truely our fellowſhip is with the Father &amp; with the Son; whilſt you are all ſtanding as ſhaddows, who are from the Light in the way to the long home <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks off, who was guided by the Light, &amp; called him in ſpirit Lord; <hi>Math</hi> 22. 43. 44. Therfore all minde the Light; Chriſt Jeſus, that you may come to witneſs him in ſpirit, to be your Lord; your bodies his Temple, And him Reigning and Ruleing therein, and not ſtill to feed your fancies, in teling of a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38331:3"/>
Reign, but examin your ſelves with the Light, wherewith you are inlightned at this preſent, and ſee who Reigns; for if ſin Reign, then Satan rules; if Chriſt Reign; then is the Devill chained, and caſt out, and all his Armor wherin he truſted. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 11. And the whole Armor of Righteouſneſs put on; That which <hi>Noah</hi> was a Preacher off, and was before <hi>Abraham;</hi> which <hi>David</hi> in Spirit cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lord; which in fulnes of time was made manifeſt, and ſaid that I, and my Father is one; and God is a Spirit; And is the ſame Yeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erday, this day and for ever, 2. <hi>Cor: 5. 16. Heb.</hi> 13. 8: We are witneſſes of it in our meaſure as <hi>Paul</hi> was, who ſaid though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth know we noe man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh; but are Epiſtles writen in one anothers hearts, with the ſpirit of the Living God; by which ſpirit all the Sons of God were guided; and he that hath not this ſpirit is none of his. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 14. (he is not ſealed.) Therfore to you all this is the word of the Lord God; Come forth of all your out-ſide formes, you are not ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, And come to the inward worſhip in ſpirit and in truth: (<hi>Iohn</hi> 4. 25) Therewith to be Sealed and Girt about; yee that once had a true tenderneſs; come and renew your firſt love; that of God in your Conſciences is my witneſs, you ſtand in ſlippery places; outward water being one of your foundamentalls as you call it; And the Light (the Rock) to you is an offence, which is coming in power &amp; great Glory to cruſh all your dead formes, and out-ſide worſhips, &amp; filthy hipocriſie that you live in; the terrors of God will ſurprize all you blind Leaders; who by faigned words and fair ſpeeches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the hearts of the ſimple; and keeps them from their teacher. (Chriſt Jeſus.) Therefore all you tender hearted ones, turne away from them which have the forme and not the power, 2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 3. 5. And you that have gon under the water for Conſcience ſake, ſuch we condemn not: but that you ſtill live in ſin, that is condemned with the Light in all your Conſciences; unto which you doe well if you take heed 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. Untill you be lead to the fear of the Lord God; that not an unſaviry word proſeed out of your Mouths; and to take up the Croſs dayly, <hi>Luke</hi> 9. 23. to all Covetouſneſs, Pride, and Ambition, which abounds amongſt you, who are called <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts;</hi> Therefore minde the Light, that by it you may come to witneſs the Redemption of your Soules which all the world cannot purchaſe, &amp; you awakned out of wickedneſs &amp; all ſelfe ſeeking, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38331:4"/>
you may no longer ſeeke ſelfe, but the Lord God; that your Souls may live, &amp; whether you will hear or for-bear, that of God in your Conſciences is my witneſs, that in word and writing, we have not ſpared to declare unto you the whole counſell of God, Without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons.</p>
            <p>Now unto all you that are tender and would hear, but dare not leaſt they ſhould caſt you out of their Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (as they call it.) I ſay unto ſuch minde the Lord our God, and try all things and hold faſt that which is Good <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 15. 21. And then wilt thou not need to be afraid of them. For the Church is in God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 11. And theſe that are alive in their Sins, are caſt out of the Church already: Therefore return unto the Light, which ſhews unto you your Sins, and puts you in minde of a day of accompt, and will let you ſee, that the longer you live in it, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er will your accompt be, and the ſader your condemnation; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleeve in the Light, and it will lead you out of Sin, And bring you to the Church in which is noe Sin; and into the I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>! to know the Doctrine of his Son; to yea and nay; in all your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications: And not to ſwear at all, neither by Heaven, nor by the Earth, nor by any other Oath <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 34. 37. And to doe unto all men as you would be done unto; &amp; then the members of the Church of the firſt born you will know, which will not nor cannot harm one the other, but are Knit and United, and joyntly and fully compacted and built together a ſpirituall houſe, where the ſpirituall man (to wit) Chriſt Jeſus Dwells, Leads, Guids, and Rules; and therein is the peace withneſſed, which paſſeth underſtanding, and the Faith unfeaigned; And the Love which is ſtronger then Death, in the Church, unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed which he hath purchaſed with his Blood, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>THOMAS LARKHAMS <hi>Erors called by the world a Miniſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Firſt. THat he hath not the Infalible ſpirit; ſecond that ſin is nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> GOD is a ſpirit &amp; infalible, &amp; he that hath not his ſpirit is none of his <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. So that out of thine own mouth thou art Judged, to be none of his; having before many people, denyed the Lord; And thy ſelfe Antichriſt, for he that is not with him is againſt him; And ſuch ſaith ſin is nothing; for which Chriſt ſuffered the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38331:4"/>
juſt for the unjuſt, and incourages the wicked, and ſaith Sin is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, then haſt thou nothing to Preach againſt; Silence for ſhame and let thy mouth be ſtopt: hath God given his Son a Ranſome for nothing? hath all the Saints declared againſt nothing? was the coming of Chriſt for the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of nothing? was it not to deſtroy the workes of the Devill? And all Sin is of him, &amp; herein thou haſt fulfilled the Scripture, Fools makes a mock of Sin <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 9.</p>
            <p>Now is the day wherin the Worlds Teachers is made manifeſt: and the blindneſs and wickedneſs of their hearts laid open: which hath taken Tythes or money (one or both) &amp; pretended to Preach againſt Sin; and now in plain words ſaith that it is nothing; and then have they taken your money all this time for nothing; as that of God in your Conſciences will me witneſs that nothing have they done for you that is good; for all the Sin that can be mentioned are you living in; and they in the like; and ſuch was never ſent of God; for he ſent holy Men and they ſpoke againſt all Sin and ſaid he that committed it, is of the Devill; 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3: 8. And ſo ſay we; and herein is the Children of God known ſro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Children of the Devill who faith Sin is nothing, then may you live as you liſt; for ſhame, can the Ranters vent filthyer things then theſe; be awarned and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them noe longer, but minde the Light wherewith you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighned and it will bring you to ſee the Vanity of all the world, and their Teachers; and with us to teſtifie againſt them; And be ſure I warne you all in the preſence of the living God: Liſten not to fleſhly Liberty for it is Egiptian bondage; and leads to utter darkneſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evermore.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. He affirmed; that the Devill is in the Church of Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Church is in God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Theſ.</hi> 11. And to that of God in all your Conſciences I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale, if there can be a greater Blaſphemer then this Man: Is the Devill in God? I ſay the Church is in God; where thou and the Devill cannot come, nor none who are not guided by the infalible Spirit, for God is pure and without ſpot or wrinkle; and ſo is his Church <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 27. But thou denying Gods Spirit; which is infalible, is given up to Blaſpheme the Lord, Bitter is thy Portion thinke upon it in thy bed of Sorrowes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly. He ſaith alſo that there is no Perfection in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Again he hath denyed the Doctrin of Chriſt, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 48.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38331:5"/>
and the worke of the Miniſtry: which is for the perfecting of the Saints, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>Coll.</hi> 1. 27. 28. And excluds all for coming into the Kingdome of heaven; where nothing that is imperfect can come; for none that is out of Chriſt can enter into the Kingdome of heaven; and they that are in Chriſt are in perfection; therefore let the honeſt hearted Judge, with that of God in you all; And if he knew but a Bridle to his Blaſphemous Tongue, and Lips, he would then know that which makes a perfect Man. <hi>Iames</hi> 3. 2. and 14. And brings to know Faith which is perfect, 'till then your hearing is vaine; as it hath been to this day; in hearing ſuch as have not the ſpirit of God which is infalible, by which all the Sons of God were guided; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 14. And ſo your Leaders cauſe you to err, and they that are lead of them are doſtroyed, <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 9: 16. And the fruits of his Lips was bitternes and curſing, Foole, and Aſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, he ſaid, he would curſe us in the name of the Lord; and had denyed the infalible ſpirit; and herein is his confuſion manifeſted. And whereas he accuſed us for denying Chriſts Merits; I ſay that which can be Merited is of ſelfe: And that which is of Chriſt is freely given; but ſuch a word is not in Scripture, as Chriſts Merits, but is ſercht from the Whore at <hi>Rrome</hi> by them, And alſo charged us with denying that Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is falce, and many ſuch things as are not worth mentioning unto which I anſwer noe other Chriſt we owne, but him who is the only begoten Son of God, full of grace and truth, the brightneſs of his glory the expreſs Jurage of his perſon: <hi>Heb.</hi> 1: 3: and 7. Who witneſſed a good Confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 6: 13. And was Crucified where it is called ſpiritually <hi>Sodam</hi> and <hi>Egipt Revel:</hi> 11: 8. And ſuffered the reproach of Sinuers the leaders of which was the Chief Prieſts, which hired <hi>Judas,</hi> read they example <hi>Math:</hi> 26: 14: 15. <hi>Math.</hi> 28: 11: 12. who denyes the infalible Spirit denyes both the Father and the Son, &amp; concludes thy ſelfe a Reprobate, and a Blaſphemer thou art out of thine owne mouth Judged, and for the ſake of the ſimple this we declare &amp; give forth under our hands.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Humphry Norton.</item>
                     <item>William Shame.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>A Reproofe to the Offenders.</head>
            <p>VVHoremongers and Addulterers God will Judge <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 4. Search the Scriptures, your whoriſh heauts is gon from God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38331:5"/>
and you are become the worſt of all Creatures; for they by Nature doth but their kinde, but you being departed from the living God, and out of the Covenant of Grace; are become abuſers of your ſelves with menkind, the Lord God abhors a whoriſh Woman for ſhe is like to a deep Ditch; and a ſtrange Woman is like to a narrow pit, their hearts are as ſnares and netts, and their hands as bands, who ſo pleaſeth God ſhall eſcape from her, but the Sinner ſhall be takne by her, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23: 27. <hi>Eccle:</hi> 7: 26: all in whom there is any fear of God minde this, for going out of the fear of God, you joyne with Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, untill your hearts be hardned, and the Devill ſeazed upon it and your ſences; and then are you laid as waſte, then doth the Lord God ſuffer Satan to ſet you in fire Soule and body and ſo conſume you and your luſts: or otherwiſe reſerve you for examples to the wicked World; the Sin is ſo Loath ſome in his ſight, for this ye know that noe Whoremaſter hath any Inheritance in the Kingdome of Chriſt, and of God <hi>Eph:</hi> 5: 5: for by means of a whoreiſh woman, a man is brought to a peece of Bread, and the Addultrous, will hunt for the pretious life; <hi>Prov:</hi> 6: 26: and for the ſake of the pretious Life is this given forth; that you who have any Conſolation in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, may all take warning, that you from your wickedneſs may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, if poſſibly to you may be found a place of Repentance, for under the heavie Curſe of God is all whores and whoremongers, &amp; filthy R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anters and Luſtfull ones who lives in the liberty of their fleſhly luſts, Let the dread of the Lord God peirce your hearts yee privat Harlots, for thus doe you require the Lord for affording you plenty of the Creatures; Drunkards &amp; Gluttons you are devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Creatures, the pit is your Portion, the Light is your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Queries unto all People to be read within.</head>
               <item>1: What is that Innocent, which Sin ſlayes?</item>
               <item>2: What is that juſt, which they that lives in pleaſures Kills? and whether they be not guilty of Innocent blood, yea, or nay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Iames</hi> 5: 5: 6.</item>
               <item>3: What is the Righteous that ſuffers by the wicked? and where it is that it ſuffers, <hi>Gene:</hi> 18: 15.</item>
               <item>4: What is that <hi>Abell</hi> whoſe blood cryes for Vengence to be taken upon <hi>Caine?</hi> which <hi>Abell</hi> the Lord hath reſpect unto; <hi>Gene:</hi> 4: 4. <hi>Heb:</hi> 12: 24.</item>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:38331:6"/>
               <item>5: What is that <hi>Iocob:</hi> which is ſound in a barren wilderneſs? &amp; in the Land of great Drought, and where that wilderneſs is? and that Droughty Land; <hi>Deut:</hi> 32: 9: 10.</item>
               <item>6. What Priſoners are theſe, which is brought out of the pit? by the blood of the Covenant? and where the pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is? wherin is noe water, <hi>Zacha:</hi> 9: 11:</item>
               <item>7: What is that witneſs which a beleever hath in himſelfe? and what hope there is for him that ſaith that there is nothing of God in him? and makes him liare? 1: <hi>Iohn:</hi> 5: 10:</item>
               <item>8. And where the grace is, which teacheth the Saints if not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? which the wicked turns into wantonneſs, <hi>Titus:</hi> 2: 11: 12.</item>
               <item>9. What Pricke that was which <hi>Saule</hi> kicked againſt whilſt he perſecuted Chriſt in his Saints, <hi>Acts</hi> 9: 5.</item>
               <item>10. What was that which when <hi>Peter</hi> Preacht prickt them at their hearts? And made them cry out men and Brethren; what ſhall we doe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2: 37.</item>
               <item>11. What was that which convicted them in their Conſciences that they could not Stone the waman that was taken in Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8: 9.</item>
               <item>12. What is that truth, which the wrath of God is revealed from heaven againſt them that holds it, in unrighteouſnes <hi>Rom</hi> 1: 18.</item>
               <item>13. And what ſeed is that, and where is it, which the Lord will power his ſpiret upon? ſpoken of in <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> 44: 3.</item>
               <item>14. And what is that ſeed of the Righteous and where is it? for whoſe ſake, the wicked ſhall not goe unpuoiſhed; although they joyne hand, in hand, <hi>Prov:</hi> 11: 21:</item>
               <item>15. What is that Righteous which periſheth and no man layeth it to heart <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 57: 1.</item>
               <item>16. What Priſoners are theſe that ſits in darknes? which Chriſt was ſent to bring out of the Priſon-houſe, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 42. 6. 7.</item>
               <item>17. What is that <hi>Zion</hi> and where is it? which is redeemed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough judgment <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1. 27.</item>
               <item>18. And who it was? that anſwered and ſaid I was wounded in the houſe of my friends, <hi>Zacha.</hi> 13. 6. And where his friends houſe is.</item>
               <item>19. And what is that which cyes out (Behold, I am) preſt under you as a Cart is preſt that is full of Sheaves, <hi>Amos</hi> 2. 13:</item>
               <item>20. And what that whole Creation is that groaneth and travelleth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38331:6"/>
in paine together untill now, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 22.</item>
               <item>21: And what Nature that was where by Chriſt ſuffered? &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you are not in the ſame Nature now, that are living in Sin? and cauſeth him to ſuffer by you dayly; ſeeing that he is the ſame yeſterday, this day, and for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 8.</item>
               <item>22. What was theat which made <hi>Judas</hi> carry the thirty peeces of Silver to the chief Prieſts (which he had received of them to betray JESVS?) and to cry out, I have ſinned in that I have betrayed the Innocent blood; <hi>Math.</hi> 27. 4.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are not given forth to the wiſe and Learned only; but alſo to the hungry and weary, and heavie Laden; to the fooliſh Ignorant &amp; blinde who are lead by the Blinde, and both are going to the Ditch, <hi>Luke.</hi> 6 39.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>To all thoſe that ſpeaks of a Perſonall Reign.</head>
            <p>To all thoſe that pretend to waite for that which they Immagin, and call a perſonall Reign, for which they have noe Scripture, but makes themſelves manifeſt to be theſe that neither knowes the Scriptures, nor the power of God; for they were writen for our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, upon whom the ends of the World are come, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 11. (Marke) they knew the end of the world come, at that time, where Sin was put away by the Sacrifice of himſelfe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 26.</p>
            <p>Now unto all you this is the word of the Lord God, you that waits out the light wherewith you are enlightned, waits out of the way, and you can never come to God, whilſt you live in Sin, your waiting is but a mocking of God, whilſt your Tongues is at liberty, and knowes not a ſtay for your mindes, (Tell me) Have not many of your Bretheren, and Siſters, pretended this waiting who are dead? (take warning) and ſaid they looked as you doe, for a Chriſt to come in anothers perſon, and not your own; are you not look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a far 'off like fooles with your Eyes abrod, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 24. and will not once looke in, and ſee who Reigns at home, whether Sin Reigne, and ſo Satan rule, or Grace Reigne through Righteouſneſs, and life through Jeſus Chriſt (marke) Here was Sins Reigne unto death, and here is Chriſts Reigne who through death, overcame him that had the power of death, which is the Devill, <hi>Rom:</hi> 5. 21. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 14. The light will let you ſee under whoſe Reign yee are, if Sin Reign, ſuffer it no longer to Reigne in your mortall bodies,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38331:7"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 12. Let no man deceive you, He that commits Sin is of the Devill, and under his Reigne, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3: 8. For Sin it is that hinders Chriſts Reign, Light and Darknes hath no communion, nor fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor concord, for the Light teſtifies againſt all the workes of Darkneſs, yea, and diſcovers Darknes it ſelfe, and noe agreement is, nor can be betwixt them, but all unrighteouſneſs muſt be caſten out, and then the Temple of God is holy, which Temple yee are, wherein he dwels, 2: <hi>Cor. 6. 14: 15: 16. 1. Cor.</hi> 6: 15: 19. Now tell me, you that looks upon the Scriptures with a carnall eye, and would have a Chriſt like unto your ſelves, what differs you from Antichriſt, who cannot own him as he is, one with the Father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10: 30: the brightneſs of his glory, the expreſs Image of his Perſon, (Behold) he is the expreſs Image of his Perſon, and upholds all things by the word of his Power, <hi>Heb:</hi> 1: 3: he abideth a Prieſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, <hi>Heb:</hi> 7: 3: Now conſider, How great this man is; which upholds all things, who was before <hi>Abraham,</hi> and is the ſame yeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erday, to day, and for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13: 8. And now yee <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> why ſtand yee gazing up into heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into heaven, is the word which upholds all things, and is hid from your eyes, It is GOD! and GOD is a Spirit, <hi>Iohn,</hi> 4. 24. Unto whom no mortall eye can approach, but by Faith was he, &amp; is he ſeen, which Faith is a myſtery held in a pure conſcience, <hi>Heb. 11. 27. 1. Tim.</hi> 3. 9. And they that are of Faith, are of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and theſe ſees Chriſt the ſame, yeſterday, today, and for ever; And to all theſe that are the leaſt ſenſible of the want of a Saviour, I ſay unto thee, whilſt thou art living in Sin, thou waites not for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt, for he was made manifeſt to take away Sin, and in him is no Sin, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. 8. The Light which ſhewes Sin being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the ſame leads to the end of the world, and brings to know a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, one to ſave you from your Sins as it is writen, they ſhall call his Name JESVS, for he ſhall ſave his people from their Sins, <hi>Math.</hi> 1. 21. The ſame teacheh to reade and underſtand that which was writen, for our admonition upon whom the ends of the world are come 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 11. Behold upon theſe was the ends of the world come, and ſo it is, upon us, who are not of the world, though living in it, yet teſtifying againſt it, that the deeds thereof are evill, that which ſhews you your cvill deeds, keepe your minde to it, and it will bring you to know every day more and more of the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38331:7"/>
of Chriſt in you; the Son of Righteouſneſs revealed in you, as it was in <hi>Paul, Gall:</hi> 1. 16: and <hi>Gall:</hi> 2. 20: the way is but one.</p>
            <p>Unto all you that are againſt this appearance to have Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in you, as he was in <hi>Paul,</hi> and in all the Sons and Daughters of God, Anſwer theſe Queries, and prove what you ſpeake by plaine Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Qu. Whether is not God and Chriſt one in every thing, yea or nay? or wherein doe they differ in any thing? and whether in this generation is he not the ſame, that he hath been in all others, (I am)</p>
            <p n="2">2. Qu. Is not all Righteouſneſs fulfiled in Chriſt? and is not God ſatisfied with this Righteouſneſs wher it is put on, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, put yee on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Qu. Whether any one man viſibly can put on another, and therein ſatisfie God? or whether any one mans Righteouſneſs will ſatisfie God for another mans Sin, yea or nay? or muſt not every Man and Woman put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt? (and then no more a carnall Chriſt,) ſeeing it is writen, woe unto him that is covered and not with my ſpirit?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Qu. And now all you that ſpeaks of a perſonall Reigne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this, from whence muſt this Chriſt come which muſt Reign perſonally? ſeeing the promiſe of God was but one, and to one, and all the Prophets of God Propheſied but of one, and they declared of what Stocke and family, and houſe, and Generation he ſhould be of, Read <hi>Math:</hi> 1: and <hi>Luke</hi> 3. and alſo where he ſhould be borne, and of whom, (to wit; a VIRGIN,) which things are fulfiled and come to paſs, we are witneſſes of it according to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Qu. Now anſwer in plain words, from whence muſt this Chriſt you waite for come, and in what Generation, and of what family, and out of what Country, and of whom muſt he be borne, that they may no longer be deceived by you, who have kept them gazing after a falce Chriſt, well may it be called gazing but leave it, and minde theſe in white apparrell which reproves you for it; <hi>Acts</hi> 1: 10: 11.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Qu. And ſeeing this Chriſt yeu preach is uncome, give me an example out of all the Scriptures of any of the Miniſters of Chriſt that preached him uncome, and what bread it is you break, if Chriſt be not come, ſeeing the Miniſter of Chriſt ſaid, the bread
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38331:8"/>
which we breake is the Lords body, and ſaid he ſpoke this to wiſe men, that they might judge what he ſaid, 1: <hi>Cor:</hi> 10: 15: 16: 17: So ſay I, Let that of God in your Conſciences judge: And you that preach Chriſt to come, whether are not you falſe witneſſes, yea or nay? and whether in the breaking of this Bread that you breake; you doe not you know not what, yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="7">7: Qu: And why you drinke wine at your meetings, ſeeing there is not any ſuch thing ſpoken off in the Scripture, that ever was uſed at the Paſſover, and if you ſay, that it is the fruit of the Vine, which you drinke freſh in the Kingdome of the Father why then doe you looke for his coming down, ſee yee him not there? of whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Dominion there is noe end; ſure you are blind:</p>
            <p n="8">8: Qu: What is the Paſſover, and what is the faſt which the Lord requires, ſeeing it is the Doctrine of Devills to ſorbid to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to abſtaine from Meates: <hi>Tim:</hi> 1. 4: 3?</p>
            <p n="9">9: Qu: And what is the ſeed unto which he gives his own body, &amp; where is, &amp; how doth he give his own body to every ſeed, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you follow his example, yea or nay? and gives your bodies to be broken, for he gave his body to be broken &amp;c: 1: <hi>Cor:</hi> 15: 38</p>
            <p n="10">10. Qu: And what is the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you eate and drinke, you have no life in you, or whether it be any carnall or viſible thing, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, that he is the expreſs Jmage of his Perſon, <hi>Heb:</hi> 1. 3: and whether God and Chriſt be not one Spirit, and whether a ſpirit hath fleſh and bones, yea, or nay? and ſee if all your wicked immaginations can divide the Father, and the Son; and their Kingdome, and them that are therein, from being all one, and in one, in whom is the vnion, and what the Union is, and wherein it ſtands?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Qu: And whether the Apoſtle was not a true Miniſter of Chriſt, who ſaid, though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, Yet now hence forth know we him no more, 2: <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 16.</p>
            <p n="12">12: Qu: And whether <hi>Iohn</hi> did not ſee the Reign of Chriſt a thouſand yeares ſince <hi>Rev:</hi> 20. 4. and whether he and his Reign be altered, or can alter or change, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, I am the Lord, I change not, <hi>Mall.</hi> 3: 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. Qu. What is it that leads you to preach &amp; to pray, &amp; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is not ſelfe yea, or nay? if Chriſt be not come, who ſent you, and whether any can preach Chriſt except they be ſent by him, &amp;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38331:8"/>
have him (what can a man preach that he hath not) who is it that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes him whitherſoever he goes &amp; hath no certaine dweling place, nor noe ſet maintenance, Woe be unto him that makes his Goſpell chargeable, and cannot live of the Goſpell, &amp; whether the Goſpell be Tythes or ſet maintenance, yea or nay? or what it is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10: 15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 18.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Qu. And whether it were not better for you who pretends to watch for the Soule and knowes not what the Soule of man is, to be ſilent, then ſtill to bring more blood upon your heads, and whilſt you are ſſpeaking to others, you your ſelves be found caſt awayes, therfore take warning, and let all fleſh keepe ſilence before the Lord untill you can give an accompt what the Soule of man is, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2. 13.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Qu. And now yee <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> ſeeing that Chriſt is come, and hath Baptized us, and all men come unto him; Tell me, whether there be any Baptiſme but one, ſeing the Apoſtle ſaith, One Lord one faith, one Baptiſme, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 5. 6. &amp; whether Baptiſme be not a Doctrine yea, or nay? if you ſay an Ordinance, whether it be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed yea or nay? ſeeing the ſcripture ſaith having aboliſhed in his fleſh the enmity, even the Law of Commandements contained in Ordinances, for to make in himſelfe of twain one new Man, ſo mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 15.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Qu. And ſeeing the Scriptures ſaith that Chriſt is the way to the Father, then is not this the Spirit of truth that leads into all truth, to the God of all truth; and doth not theſe that looke for a Chriſt to come, deny the way to God, Tell me, what way muſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple goe to God, if Chriſt be not come, ſeeing they dye daily, <hi>John 14. 6. John:</hi> 16: 30.</p>
            <p>VNTO all you that ſay you would refraine ſuch &amp; ſuch things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had you power (conſider) what power are you under, is God unjuſt; Doth he require any thing of any Creature to be done, or not done, but he gives ſtrength according to what he requires; his hand is not ſhortned, nor his power ſtraitned; it is the ſame yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and for ever, for the ſame which reproves for Sin, gives ſtrength againſt Sin: unto all that beleeve in it, for the Croſs of Chriſt which is the power of God is to be taken up dayly: ſo that you whoſe mindes are turned tawards God take heed of ſlighting the Croſs for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38331:9"/>
in ſo doing thou flees the power of God; And ſuch Spirits will ſay if it be his minde he will conſtraine me whether I will or not; I cannot reſiſt him; I ſay in ſomuch as thou art not obedient to the leaſt of his reproofes thou reſiſts him; and art he that ſaith in heart I will none of thy reproofes; Unto ſuch I ſay, the Lord God is juſt, and will be glorified in thy deſtruction; And contrary to thy will; will cut thee off, and give thy portion amongſt the unbeleevers; in the Lake; therfore take warning, and minde that which reproves you for your evill deeads, and beleeve in it, for in the ſame is the power of God unto Salvation received and injoyed; <hi>Jſaiah 59: 1. 1. Cor. 1: 18. Math.</hi> 24: 51.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HVMPHRY NORTON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
